with refugees because I wanted
مع اللاجئين لأنني أردت
to make a difference,
أن أحدث تغييراً،
and making a difference starts
ويبدأ إحداث التغيير
with telling their stories.
برواية قصصهم.
So when I meet refugees,
لذلك عندما أقابل اللاجئين،
I always ask them questions.
أسألهم دائما هذه الأسئلة.
Who bombed your house?
من فجر منزلك؟
Who killed your son?
من قتل ولدك؟
Did the rest of your family make it out alive?
هل بقي أفراد عائلتك على قيد الحياة؟
How are you coping
كيف تتغلب على مصاعب
in your life in exile?
الحياة في المنفى؟
But there's one question that always seems to me
ولكن يبقى هذا السؤال الذي طالما بدا لي
to be most revealing, and that is:
السؤال الأكثر إيحاء وهو:
What did you take?
ماذا حملت معك؟
What was that most important thing
ما هو الشيء الأكثر أهمية
that you had to take with you
الذي توجب عليك حمله
when the bombs were exploding in your town,
عندما كانت القنابل تتفجر في بلدتك
and the armed gangs were approaching your house?
و عندما كانت العصابات المسلحة تقترب من منزلك؟
A Syrian refugee boy I know
أخبرني طفل سوري لاجئ أعرفه
told me that he didn't hesitate
بأنه لم يتردد
when his life was in imminent danger.
عندما كانت حياته في خطر وشيك.
He took his high school diploma,
حمل شهادته الثانوية،
and later he told me why.
وأخبرني لاحقا بالسبب،
He said, "I took my high school diploma
قال لي: "حملت شهادتي الثانوية
because my life depended on it."
لأن حياتي تعتمد عليها."
And he would risk his life to get that diploma.
وأنه مستعد للمخاطرة بحياته من أجلها.
On his way to school, he would dodge snipers.
وفي طريقه إلى المدرسة، يراوغ هذا الصبي القناصة.
His classroom sometimes shook
وأحيانا تهتز حجرة صفه
with the sound of bombs and shelling,
من أصوات القنابل والقصف الصاروخي،
and his mother told me,
وأخبرتني والدته،
"Every day, I would say to him every morning,
"كلّ يوم أقول له في الصباح،
'Honey, please don't go to school.'"
أرجوك يا عزيزي ألا تذهب إلى المدرسة."
And when he insisted, she said,
ولكنه عندما يصر على الذهاب، قالت لي:
"I would hug him as if it were for the last time."
"أحضنه كما لو أنني لن أراه مجددا."
But he said to his mother,
ولكنه يجيب والدته بقوله،
"We're all afraid,
"نحن جميعاً خائفون،
but our determination to graduate
ولكن إصرارنا على التخرج
is stronger than our fear."
أقوى من خوفنا."
But one day, the family got terrible news.
ولكن في أحد الأيام، تلقت العائلة أخباراً سيئة.
Hany's aunt, his uncle and his cousin
عمة هاني وعمه وابن عمه
were murdered in their homes for refusing
جميعهم قتلوا في منازلهم
to leave their house.
لرفضهم مغادرتها.
Their throats were slit.
قُطّعت أعناقهم.
It was time to flee.
حانت ساعة الرحيل.
They left that day, right away, in their car,
غادروا مباشرة في ذلك اليوم في سيارتهم،
Hany hidden in the back because they were facing
و كان هاني مختبئاً في مؤخرة السيارة لأنهم كانوا يواجهون
And they would cross the border into Lebanon,
أرادوا عبور الحدود إلى لبنان
where they would find peace.
حيث يجدون الأمان.
But they would begin a life of grueling hardship
ولكنهم سيبدأون الاّن حياة من العذاب المرير
and monotony.
والرتابة.
They had no choice but to build a shack
لا خيار أمامهم إلا بناء كوخ
on the side of a muddy field,
على جانب حقل موحل،
and this is Hany's brother Ashraf,
وها هو أشرف شقيق هاني،
who plays outside.
الذي يلعب بالخارج.
And that day, they joined
في ذلك اليوم، انضمت العائلة
the biggest population of refugees in the world,
إلى أكبر تجمع للاجئين في العالم،
in a country, Lebanon, that is tiny.
في بلد صغير مثل لبنان.
It only has four million citizens,
إنه بلد يضم أربعة ملايين مواطن فقط،
and there are one million Syrian refugees living there.
ومليون لاجئ سوري يعيشون هناك.
There's not a town, a city or a village
حيث لا تخلو بلدة أو مدينة أو قرية
that is not host to Syrian refugees.
من لاجئين سوريين.
This is generosity and humanity
هذا هو الكرم و هذه هي الإنسانية،
that is remarkable.
هذا أمر رائع.
Think about it this way, proportionately.
انظروا إلى الأمر بهذه الطريقة
It would be as if
من حيث التناسب، الأمر يشبه كأن
the entire population of Germany,
جميع سكان ألمانيا،
80 million people,
والبالغ عددهم ثمانين مليون،
would flee to the United States in just three years.
هاجروا إلى الولايات المتحدة في غضون ثلاث سنوات فقط.
Half of the entire population of Syria
إن نصف الشعب السوري
is now uprooted,
أصبح نازحاً الآن،
most of them inside the country.
و معظمهم نازحون داخل البلاد.
Six and a half million people
ستة ملايين ونصف
have fled for their lives.
فروا للنجاة بحياتهم.
Over and well over three million people
أكثر من ثلاثة ملايين شخص
have crossed the borders
قد عبروا الحدود
and have found sanctuary in the neighboring countries,
ووجدوا ملجئاً في بلدان الجوار،
and only a small proportion, as you see,
ونسبة صغيرة كما ترون
have moved on to Europe.
انتقلت لتعيش في أوروبا.
What I find most worrying
أكثر ما أجده مدعاة للقلق
is that half of all Syrian refugees are children.
هو أن نصف اللاجئين السوريين هم من الأطفال.
I took this picture of this little girl.
التقطت هذه الصوره لفتاة صغيرة،
It was just two hours after she had arrived
بعد ساعتين فقط من وصولها
after a long trek from Syria into Jordan.
بعد رحلة طويلة من سورية باتجاه الأردن.
And most troubling of all
وأكثر ما يقلق
is that only 20 percent of Syrian refugee children
هو أن عشرين بالمئة فقط من اللاجئين السوريين الأطفال
are in school in Lebanon.
يرتادون المدارس في لبنان.
And yet, Syrian refugee children,
وعلاوة على ذلك، فإن كل اللاجئين السوريين الأطفال
all refugee children tell us
بل كل اللاجئين الأطفال يخبرونا بأن
education is the most important thing in their lives.
التعليم هو أكثر الأمور أهمية في حياتهم.
Why? Because it allows them to think of their future
لماذا؟ لأنه يسمح لهم بالتفكير بمستقبلهم
rather than the nightmare of their past.
بدلاً من كوابيس ماضيهم.
It allows them to think of hope rather than hatred.
يجعلهم التعليم يفكرون بالأمل بدل الكراهية.
I'm reminded of a recent visit I took
تذكرت زيارة قمت بها مؤخراً إلى
to a Syrian refugee camp in northern Iraq,
مخيم لللاجئين السوريين في شمال العراق،
and I met this girl,
قابلت هناك هذه الفتاة،
and I thought, "She's beautiful,"
قلت بنفسي" كم هي جميلة"،
and I went up to her and asked her,
واتجهت نحوها و سألتها،
"Can I take your picture?"
" هل يمكنني التقاط صورة لك؟"
And she said yes,
فقالت "نعم"،
but she refused to smile.
ولكنها رفضت أن تبتسم.
I think she couldn't,
أعتقد بأنها لم تستطع أن تبتسم،
because I think she must realize that she represents
لأنها أيقنت بأنها تمثل
a lost generation of Syrian refugee children,
جيلاً تائهاً من اللاجئين السوريين الأطفال،
a generation isolated and frustrated.
جيلاً منعزلاً ومحبطاً،
And yet, look at what they fled:
انظروا ما الذي فروا منه:
utter destruction,
دمار شامل،
buildings, industries, schools, roads, homes.
مبان ومصانع ومدارس وطرقات ومنازل،
Hany's home was also destroyed.
منزل هاني دمر أيضاً.
This will need to be rebuilt
هذا كله بحاجة لإعادة إعمار
by architects, by engineers, by electricians.
بيد بنائين ومهندسين وكهربائيين.
Communities will need teachers and lawyers
المجتمعات بحاجة إلى معلمين ومحامين
and politicians interested in reconciliation
ورجال سياسة همهم المصالحة
and not revenge.
لا الأخذ بالثأر.
Shouldn't this be rebuilt
أليس من المفروض أن تقوم بالإعمار
by the people with the largest stake,
تلك الفئة الأكبر من الشعب،
the societies in exile, the refugees?
تلك الفئة في المنفى، اللاجئون ؟
Refugees have a lot of time
لدى اللاجئين الكثير من الوقت
to prepare for their return.
ليستعدوا من أجل عودتهم.
You might imagine that being a refugee
ربما تعتقدون بأن اللجوء
is just a temporary state.
هو حالة مؤقتة.
Well far from it.
حسناً، بعيداً عن هذا الاعتقاد،
With wars going on and on,
ومع استمرار الحرب،
the average time a refugee will spend in exile
فإن معدل المدة التي يقضيها اللاجئ في المنفى
is 17 years.
هو سبعة عشر عاماً.
Hany was into his second year in limbo
كان هاني في عامه الثاني في المنفى
when I went to visit him recently,
عندما ذهبت لزيارته مؤخراً،
and we conducted our entire conversation in English,
وأجرينا المقابلة بأكملها باللغة الإنكليزية
which he confessed to me he learned
والتي اعترف هاني لي بتعلمها
from reading all of Dan Brown's novels
بعد قراءته لروايات "دان براون"
and from listening to American rap.
ومن خلال سماعه لموسيقى الراب الأمريكية.
We also spent some nice moments of laughter
كما قضينا بعض اللحظات الممتعة من الضحك
and fun with his beloved brother Ashraf.
والمتعة مع أخيه أشرف والذي يحبه هاني جداً.
But I'll never forget what he told me
ولكنني لن أنسى أبداً ما أخبرني إياه
when we ended our conversation that day.
عندما انتهينا من الحوار في ذلك اليوم.
He said to me,
قال لي:
"If I am not a student, I am nothing."
"لو لم أكن تلميذاً، فأنا لا قيمة لي."
Hany is one of 50 million people
هاني، واحد من خمسين مليون شخص
uprooted in this world today.
نازح في هذا العالم، اليوم.
Never since World War II
لم يحدث منذ الحرب العالمية الثانية
have so many people been forcibly displaced.
أن يجبر هذا العدد الهائل من البشر على النزوح.
So while we're making sweeping progress
فبينما نحرز تقدماً هائلاً
in human health,
في مجال الصحة الإنسانية
in technology, in education and design,
وفي التكنولوجيا والتعليم والتصميم،
we are doing dangerously little
نحن وعلى نحو خطير لا نقوم إلا بالشيء القليل
to help the victims
لمساعدة الضحايا
and we are doing far too little
بل نقوم بجهد أقل أيضاً
to stop and prevent
لوقف ومنع
the wars that are driving them from their homes.
الحروب التي تدفع هؤلاء الضحايا إلى النزوح من أوطانهم.
And there are more and more victims.
ويزداد عدد الضحايا أكثر فأكثر
Every day, on average,
كل يوم، بمعدل
by the end of this day,
سيصل مع نهاية هذا اليوم إلى
32,000 people will be forcibly displaced
اثنين وثلاثين ألف شخص نازح قسري
from their homes —
من أوطانهم -
32,000 people.
اثنين وثلاثين ألف شخص.
They flee across borders like this one.
فروا عبر الحدود مثل هذه الصورة.
We captured this on the Syrian border to Jordan,
التقطنا هذه الصورة على الحدود السورية الأردنية،
and this is a typical day.
وهذا يوم إعتيادي.
Or they flee on unseaworthy and overcrowded boats,
أو يفرون على قوارب مكتظة وغير صالحة للإبحار،
risking their lives in this case
يجازفون بحياتهم بهذا الشكل
just to reach safety in Europe.
فقط ليصلوا بسلام إلى أوروبا.
This Syrian young man
هذا الشاب السوري
survived one of these boats that capsized —
نجا من إحدى هذه القوارب التي انقلبت -
most of the people drowned —
معظم الذين كانوا على متنه غرقوا -
and he told us,
وأخبرنا هذا الشاب قائلاً:
"Syrians are just looking for a quiet place
"يبحث السوريون فقط عن مكان اّمن،
where nobody hurts you,
مكان لا يؤذيك فيه أحد،
where nobody humiliates you,
ولا يذلّك أحد،
and where nobody kills you."
ولا يقتلك أحد."
Well, I think that should be the minimum.
حسناً، أعتقد بأن هذا أقل ما يمكن تأمينه لهم.
How about a place of healing,
ولكن ماذا عن مكان للشفاء
of learning,
وللتعلم
and even opportunity?
أوحتى تأمين الفرص؟
Americans and Europeans
في أوروبا وأميريكا لديهم الانطباع
have the impression that proportionally
بأن أعداداً كبيرة
huge numbers of refugees are coming
من اللاجئين سيصلون
to their country,
إلى بلادهم،
but the reality is
ولكن الحقيقة تظهر بأن
that 86 percent, the vast majority of refugees,
ثمانية وستين بالمئة من اللاجئين، وهي النسبة الأكبر،
are living in the developing world,
يعيشون في البلدان النامية،
in countries struggling with their own insecurity,
في بلدان تعاني من حالة انعدام الأمن،
with their own issues of helping their own populations
تعاني من قضايا تمنعها من مساعدة شعوبها
and poverty.
وتعاني الفقر أيضاً.
So wealthy countries in the world should recognize
على البلدان الثرية في العالم أن تعترف
the humanity and the generosity of the countries
بمقدار الإنسانية والكرم لتلك البلدان
that are hosting so many refugees.
التي تستضيف أعداداً كبيرة من اللاجئين.
And all countries should make sure that no one
وعلى كل البلدان أن تضمن
fleeing war and persecution
بأن لا تغلق الحدود أمام أي شخص
arrives at a closed border.
يفرّ من الحرب والاضطهاد.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
But there is something more that we can do
ولكن يمكننا أن نقوم بما هو أكثر
than just simply helping refugees survive.
من مجرّد مساعدة اللاجئين على البقاء على قيد الحياة.
We can help them thrive.
يمكننا أن نساعدهم على النجاح.
We should think of refugee camps and communities
علينا أن نعتبر مخيمات و تجمعات اللاجئين
as more than just temporary population centers
أكثرمن كونها مراكز سكانية مؤقتة
where people languish
يقبع فيها اللاجئون
waiting for the war to end.
ينتظرون نهاية الحرب.
Rather, as centers of excellence,
بدلاً من ذلك يجب أن نعتبرها مراكز للتميّز،
where refugees can triumph over their trauma
حيث يمكن لللاجئين أن ينتصروا على اّلامهم
and train for the day that they can go home
ويتم تدريبهم من أجل اليوم الذي سيعودون فيه إلى المنزل
as agents of positive change
ليؤدوا دورهم في التغيير الإيجابي
and social transformation.
والتحول الإجتماعي.
It makes so much sense,
هكذا يصبح الأمر منطقياً،
but I'm reminded of the terrible war in Somalia
أتذكّر الحرب المريعة في الصومال
that has been raging on for 22 years.
والتي بقيت مشتعلة لمدة اثنين وعشرين عاماً.
And imagine living in this camp.
وأتخيل المعيشة في هذا المخيم.
I visited this camp.
زرت هذا المخيم
It's in Djibouti, neighboring Somalia,
في جيبوتي المجاورة للصومال،
and it was so remote
و كان المخيم في منطقة نائية جداً
that we had to take a helicopter to fly there.
بحيث كان علينا أن نستقل المروحية للوصول إليه.
It was dusty and it was terribly hot.
كان الجو مغبراً وحاراً جداً،
And we went to visit a school
وذهبنا لزيارة مدرسة
and started talking to the children,
وبدأنا نتحدث مع الأطفال،
and then I saw this girl across the room
وثم رأيت هذه الفتاة في أنحاء الغرفة
who looked to me to be the same age
والتي بدت لي بعمر ابنتي
as my own daughter, and I went up and talked to her.
فأقبلت عليها وتحدثت معها.
And I asked her the questions
سألتها تلك الأسئلة
that grown-ups ask kids,
التي يسألها البالغون للأطفال،
like, "What is your favorite subject?"
مثل "ما هو الموضوع الدراسي الذي تفضله؟"
and, "What do you want to be when you grow up?"
و"ماذا تريدين أن تصبحي عندما تكبرين؟"
And this is when her face turned blank,
في هذه اللحظة رأيت على وجهها حالة من الذهول،
and she said to me,
قالت لي:
"I have no future.
"لم يعد لدي مستقبل،
My schooling days are over."
انتهت أيام المدرسة بالنسبة لي."
And I thought, there must be some misunderstanding,
واعتقدت حينها بوجود سوء فهم ما
so I turned to my colleague
لذلك التفتّ إلى زميلتي
and she confirmed to me
وأكدّت لي
there is no funding for secondary education
بأنه لا تمويل للتعليم الثانوي
in this camp.
في هذا المخيم.
And how I wished at that moment
كم تمنيت في تلك اللحظة
that I could say to her,
أن أستطيع أن أقول لها:
"We will build you a school."
"سنقوم ببناء مدرسة لكم."
And I also thought, what a waste.
وقلت في نفسي يا لها من خسارة.
She should be and she is
هذه الفتاة يفترض أن تكون بل إنها بالفعل
the future of Somalia.
مستقبل الصومال.
A boy named Jacob Atem
صبي يدعى"يعقوب عاتم "
had a different chance, but not before he experienced
كانت فرصته مختلفة ولكن ليس قبل أن يمر
terribly tragedy.
بمأساة رهيبة.
He watched — this is in Sudan —
لقد حدث هذا في السودان، شاهد هذا الصبي
as his village — he was only seven years old —
قريته، وهو لم يتجاوز السابعة من عمره،
burned to the ground, and he learned
تتحول إلى رماد، وعلم بأن
that his mother and his father
والدته ووالده
and his entire family
وعائلته بأكملها
were killed that day.
قتلوا ذلك اليوم.
Only his cousin survived, and the two of them
نجا ابن عمه فقط، وظلّ كلاهما
walked for seven months —
يمشيان لبضعة أشهر -
this is boys like him —
هؤلاء أولاد مثلهم -
chased and pursued by wild animals and armed gangs,
تمت ملاحقتهم وتعقبهم بواسطة حيوانات متوحشة وعصابات مسلحة،
and they finally made it to refugee camps
وتمكن كلاهما من الوصول أخيراً إلى مخيمات اللاجئين
where they found safety,
حيث وجدوا الأمان،
and he would spend the next seven years
وسيمضي السنوات السبع القادمة
in Kenya in a refugee camp.
في مخيم لاجئين في كينيا.
But his life changed
ولكن حياته تغيرت
when he got the chance to be resettled
عندما حصل على فرصة لإعادة توطينه
to the United States,
في الولايات المتحدة،
and he found love in a foster family
ووجد الحبّ عند عائلة تبنته
and he was able to go to school,
وتمكن من الذهاب إلى المدرسة،
and he wanted me to share with you
وأراد منّي أن أشارككم
this proud moment
لحظة الفخرهذه
when he graduated from university.
عندما تخرج من الجامعة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I spoke to him on Skype the other day,
تحدثت معه عبر (السكايب) ذات يوم
pursuing his Ph.D. in public health,
يسعى للحصول على شهادة الدكتوراه في الصحة العامة،
and he proudly told me how he was able to raise
وأخبرني بكل فخر كيف تمكّن من جمع
enough funds from the American public
تمويل كاف من العامة في أميريكا
to establish a health clinic back in his village
ليؤسس عيادة في قريته
back home.
هناك في وطنه.
So I want to take you back to Hany.
الاّن أودّ أن أعود وأخبركم عن هاني.
When I told him I was going to have the chance
عندما أخبرته بأن الفرصة ستسنح لي
to speak to you here on the TED stage,
لأتحدث عنه هنا على منصة ( TED )،
he allowed me to read you a poem
أذن لي بأن أقرأ لكم قصيدة
that he sent in an email to me.
أرسلها لي عبر الإيميل.
He wrote:
كتب في القصيدة:
"I miss myself,
" أشتاق لنفسي
my friends,
ولأصدقائي
times of reading novels or writing poems,
ولأوقات قراءة الروايات وكتابة القصائد
birds and tea in the morning.
ولعصافير وشاي الصباح
My room, my books, myself,
لغرفتي ولكتبي ولنفسي
and everything that was making me smile.
ولكل شيء كان يدعوني للضحك.
Oh, oh, I had so many dreams
اّه اّه كم كان لدي من أحلام
that were about to be realized."
كانت على وشك أن تتحقق."
So here is my point:
ما أقصده هو:
Not investing in refugees
إن عدم الاستثمار في شؤون اللاجئين
is a huge missed opportunity.
هو فرصة مهمة ضائعة.
Leave them abandoned,
إن تركهم منعزلين
and they risk exploitation and abuse,
يتعرضون لخطر الاستغلال وسوء المعاملة
and leave them unskilled and uneducated,
وتركهم دون مهارة أو تعليم
and delay by years the return
تؤخر سنوات عودتهم
to peace and prosperity in their countries.
إلى حالة الأمن والازدهار في بلادهم.
I believe how we treat the uprooted
أعتقد بأن الطريقة التي نتعامل بها مع النازحين
will shape the future of our world.
سترسم مستقبل عالمنا.
The victims of war can hold the keys
يمكن لضحايا الحروب أن يصنعوا
to lasting peace,
السلام الدائم،
and it's the refugees
إنهم اللاجئون
who can stop the cycle of violence.
من يمكنهم إيقاف حلقة العنف.
Hany is at a tipping point.
هاني الآن عند نقطة تحول.
We would love to help him go to university
نودّ لو نساعده على الذهاب إلى الجامعة
and to become an engineer,
ونساعده ليصبح مهندساً،
but our funds are prioritized for the basics in life:
ولكن الأولوية لتمويلكم يركز على أساسيات الحياة:
tents and blankets and mattresses and kitchen sets,
الخيام والبطانيات والفرش وأدوات المطبخ
food rations and a bit of medicine.
والحصص الغذائية والقليل من الدواء.
University is a luxury.
الجامعة هي من الكماليات.
But leave him to languish in this muddy field,
ولكن اتركوا هاني في هذا الحقل الموحل،
and he will become a member
و سيصبح عضواً
of a lost generation.
من جيل ضائع.
Hany's story is a tragedy,
إن قصة هاني هي مأساة،
but it doesn't have to end that way.
ولكن ليس من الضروري أن تنتهي بهذه الطريقة.
Thank you.
أشكركم.